<profile xmlns="http://ainq.com/ig-definition" id="SANER" chapter='1' codingsystems="SanerBedType" valuesets="BedLocationOperationalStatus BedProperty BedType">
	<domain id="AI">
	    <org>Audacious Inquiry</org>
	    <name>Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response</name>
	    <description></description>
	    <overview file="SANER-overview.md"/>
	</domain>
    <name>Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response</name>
    <description>The Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response Implementation Guide enables transmission
of high level situational awareness information from inpatient facilities to centralized data repositories
to support the treatment of novel influenza-like illness.
    </description>
    <!-- overview is optional -->
    <overview file="SANER-overview.md"/>
    <!-- option is optional and repeatable -->
    <option id="Dump">
        <name>Storage Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the Storage Option supports the ability to exchange FHIR Resources through
various means of simple data transfer, rather than directly through a FHIR API call. This include mechanisms such
as SFTP, S3 Blob Storage, Azure Blob Storage, a Message Queue, https: File Download, File System dumps, or Direct Messages with a
data payload. Supported formats include JSON, XML and NDJSON.
        </description>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>A <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> actor implementing the Storage Option uses external storage to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>A <ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> actor implementing the Storage Option uses external storage to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="API">
        <name>API Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the API Option supports the
ability to exchange FHIR Resources using [FHIR RESTful APIs](http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/http.html).</description>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>An <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> actor implementing the API option uses FHIR RESTful APIs to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An <ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> actor implementing the API option uses FHIR RESTful APIs to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Push">
	    <name>Push Option</name>
	    <description>An actor implementing the Push Option supports the periodic push of resources
describing the current status of health delivery resources to a centralized collection point.
	    </description>
	    <overview/>
	    <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
	        <description>A Measure Source implementing the Push Option periodically sends updates to a
<ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> using the <ref tx='PUSH-TX'/> transaction.</description>
	    </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Push Option periodically recieves updates from the
<ref actor='MeasureSource'/> using the <ref tx='PUSH-TX'/> transaction.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Pull">
        <name>Pull Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the Pull Option supports the periodic pull resources
describing the current status of selected health delivery resources.</description>
        <overview/>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
           <description>A Measure Source implementing the Pull Option is periodically queried by an
<ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> using the <ref tx='PULL-TX'/> transaction to enable collection of the current status.
</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Pull Option periodically queries a
<ref actor='MeasureSource'/> using the <ref tx='PULL-TX'/> transaction to enable collection of the current status.
            </description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <!-- standard is repeatable -->
    <standard id="FHIR-R4">
        <name>HL7 FHIR Release 4.0</name>
        <url>http://www.hl7.org/FHIR/R4</url>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-7230">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc7230.html</url>
        <name>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP/1.1</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-7540">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc7540.html</url>
        <name>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP/2</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-3986">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.html</url>
        <name>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-4627">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc4627.html</url>
        <name>The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-6585">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc6585.html</url>
        <name>Additional HTTP Status Codes</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="NDJSON">
        <url>http://ndjson.org/</url>
        <name>Newline Delimited JSON</name>
    </standard>

    <!-- usecase is optional and repeatable -->
    <usecase id="GETBEDS" actors="MeasureSource MeasureConsumer" transactions="PULL-TX PUSH-TX" content="">
	    <name>Collecting Hospital and Ventilator Measures</name>
        <description>This use case addresses the collection and exchange of data from several information systems in a Facility
to a centralized reporting system that communicates to Public Health. The ICU/Central Monitoring System collects data
for multiple data elements by examining messages recieved and data in its database, and then reports these to a Measure Collector
within the hospital.</description>
	    <overview file='SANER-getbeds.md'/>
	    <step id="GETVALUES" from="ICU/Central Monitoring System" to="ICU/Central Monitoring System" returns="now">
	        <name>ICU/Central Monitoring System collects data</name>
	        <description>The ICU/Central Monitoring System is triggered (by request or schedule) to generate
a report on ICU beds and equipment, including ventilated patients in ED/Overflow w/ COVID-19,
Total ICU Beds, Occupied ICU Beds, Total Ventilators, Ventilators in Use.</description>
            <overview>
   1. The system collects information about ventilators outside the ICU for which the associated patient
was admitted for suspected or confirmed COVID-19. It can makes the determination of suspected/confirmed COVID-19 from
the DG1 segment of the ADT message it recieved regarding the patient.
   2. The system counts the number of ICU beds that it has been configured to recognize and which are operational
   3. The system counts the number of ICU beds that are transmitting telemetry (patient monitoring) information.
   4. The system counts the number of ventilators that it has been configured to recognize and which are operational
   5. The system counts the number of ventilators that are transmitting telemetry data to it in the ICU.
            </overview>
	        <step id="REPORTVALUES-1.5-2.4-7" from="ICU/Central Monitoring System" to="Measure Collector" returns="now">
                <name>ICU/Central Monitoring System Reports&#xA;on multiple data elements&#xA;(measure populations)</name>
                <description>Multiple collected values are aggregated into a report which is then transmitted to the Measure Collector.</description>
	        </step>
	    </step>

	    <step id="GETHOSPITALBEDS" from="Bed Management System" to="Measure Collector" returns="now">
	       <name>Bed Management System Reports&#xA;on multiple data elements&#xA;(measure populations)</name>
	       <description>The Hospitals Bed Management System collects data for multiple data elements by
examining messages recieved and data in its database, and then reports these to a Measure Collector
within the hospital.</description>
            <overview>
   1. The Bed Management System examines master file data to count the total number of beds in the hospital,
as well as those beds specifically identified as being for acute (inpatient) care. The Bed Management solution can be a component
of the EHR, or as occurs in some hospital settings, a third party solution that integrates with the EHR (usually through ADT and master file
messages).
   2. The bed management system counts the occupied beds (based on current state of each bed) as tracked through
state changes communicated through ADT messages.  The Bed Management solution might be used to support housekeeping, or to support an [electronic
bedboard](https://it.johnshopkins.edu/services/applications/administrative/ebb.html) that might used by a hospital
"[Bed Czar](http://www.ihi.org/resources/Pages/Changes/RealTimeDemandCapacityManagement.aspx)."</overview>
	    </step>

	    <step id="GETCOVID19DATA" from="EHR" to="Measure Collector" returns="now">
           <name>EHR System reports&#xA;on multiple data elements&#xA;(measure populations)</name>
           <description>The Hospital's EHR collects data for multiple data elements.</description>
            <overview>
   1. The EHR collects data on hospitalized patients w/ COVID-19.
   2. The EHR collects data on hospitalized patients diagnosed with COVID-19 14 days after admission.
   3. The EHR collects data on patient deaths due to COVID-19.</overview>
        </step>

        <step id="GETEDDATA" from="ED System" to="Measure Collector" returns="now">
           <name>The ED System reports&#xA;on patients in the ED and/or overflow area.</name>
        </step>

	    <step id="BED-STEP1" from="Measure Collector" to="Measure Collector" returns="now">
            <name>Measure Collector aggregates reports for&#xA;transmission to a Public Health Agency</name>
            <description>Either periodically on some schedule configured for the hospital, or upon recieving a
full set of data, the Measure Collector gathers a set of results from different systems
that have communicated them, putting together a complete MeasureReport for later reporting to the Public Health Agency.</description>
	    </step>
        <step id="BED-STEP3" from="Measure Collector" to="Public Health Agency" returns="now">
            <name>Transmit Aggregated MeasureReport Data</name>
            <description>In a "push" model, the Measure Collector sends the aggregated MeasureReport to a MeasureConsumer (e.g., a Public
            Health endpoint used for measure transmission).</description>
        </step>
	    <step id="BED-STEP4" to="Measure Collector" from="Public Health Agency" returns="now">
            <name>A Public Health Agency queries the&#xA;hospitals Measure Collector&#xA;for the most recent reports.</name>
            <description>As an alternative to push, the Public Health Agency can also "pull" data by querying the Hospitals
"Measure Collector" endpoint (in fact, a FHIR Server with some additional features supporting aggregation).</description>
            <return id="BED-STEP5" returns="now">
                <name>Transmit Aggregated MeasureReport Data</name>
                <description>The Measure Collector sends the aggregated MeasureReports to the requesting Public Health Agency.</description>
            </return>
        </step>
    </usecase>
    <usecase id="VIEWREPORTS" actors="MeasureConsumer MeasureIntermediary" transactions="REPORT-TX" content="">
        <name>Reporting on A Measure</name>
        <description>A public health user queries a reporting system to report on a measure for a region.</description>
        <!-- overview is optional -->
        <overview>In this use case, we see the classic "dashboard" panel, where a public health user
selects a region, and one or more measures (or functions of measures) to report on, and the data is presented
to them in an easy to view format.</overview>
        <step id="Aggregating-STEP2" from="MeasureIntermediary" to="MeasureSource" returns="now">
                <name>Measure Consumer component of a Measure Intermediary gathers data from one or Measure Sources</name>
                <description>The Measure Intermediary, acting as a Measure Consumer gathers and aggregates data (possibly computing a function with other associated data) from one or more Measure Sources,
and makes them available through a Measure Source interface it provides.</description>
                <overview>The specific ordering in which gathering and aggregation is performed is not further specified
by this implementation guide. It is shown as occuring before the user initiates the query here, but could also occur
after. However, for many cases, geospatial systems can likely do a better job if the aggregation is done ahead of time.
The application of a function to the data can enable a measure such as # of cases to be combined with other data such as
population for the area to report # of cases per 10K population, or similar functions to better present data
in a way that allows it to be reported using comparable scales.</overview>
        </step>
        <step id="Reporting-STEP1" from="Public Health User" to="MeasureConsumer" returns="now">
            <name>User Initiates Search</name>
            <description>The Public Health User navigates to a web page where collected data is reported.</description>
            <overview>The user selects a geographic region and an issue of concern (e.g., beds, ventilators, PPE).  The Measure Consumer collects the appropriate reports
and displays the results.</overview>
            <return>
                <name>Display Results</name>
                <description>The Measure Consumer displays an overview of aggregated regional results to the
user, and additional links which enable navigation to finer grained or alternative displays.</description>
                <overview>Data can be displayed as aggregated or fine-grained status information based
on the current focus of the public health user.  It may be shown as a map, a table, or a graph.</overview>
            </return>
        </step>
        <step id="Reporting-STEP2" from="Public Health User" to="MeasureConsumer" returns="now">
            <name>User refines Focus or Form of Display</name>
            <description>The Public Health User selects a new form of display (e.g., Map, table or graph) or refines their
focus (e.g., wider or smaller region).</description>
            <return>
                <name>Display Refined Results</name>
                <description>The Measure Repository modifies the users focus and reporting format</description>
            </return>
        </step>
    </usecase>
    <!--  Other Use Cases can describe options -->
    <actor id="MeasureSource">
        <name>Measure Source</name>
        <description>The Measure Source Actor reports results for a single facility, collection of facilities or aggregated data for a region.</description>
        <!-- overview is optional -->
        <overview>
In a single facility, or organization, the Measure Source Actor will compile data directly from the facility
or organization source systems.

A Measure Source may also exist in an Aggregator, Intermediary or Bridging role.  In this guide we will use
the term Intermediary to describe these roles.

A Measure Source provides the FHIR data that is used by a Measure Consumer.
</overview>
        <supports-tx transaction="PULL-TX" as="server" required-with-options="Pull">
            <role>Reports on selected data in response to a query.</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PUSH-TX" as="client" required-with-options="Push">
            <role>Periodically generates data for a Measure Consumer.</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="COLLECT-R1" at-least-one="Pull Push"/>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="COLLECT-R2" at-least-one="API Dump"/>
    </actor>

    <actor id="MeasureConsumer">
        <name>Measure Consumer</name>
        <description>The Measure Consumer provides access to aggregated or fine-grained
data gathered from one or more Measure Sources.
        </description>
        <overview>
The Measure Consumer provides the ability to report on data from one or more Measure Sources.

In the case of a single facility or organization the Measure Consumer is reporting the data at aggregated
or varying levels of granularity using data extracted from a Measure Source.
        </overview>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="REPORT-R1" at-least-one="Pull Push"/>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="REPORT-R1" at-least-one="API Dump"/>

        <requires-tx transaction="REPORT-TX" as="self">
            <role>Display or transmits reports using availability data</role>
        </requires-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PULL-TX" as="client" required-with-options="Pull">
            <role>Collects data for reporting</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PUSH-TX" as="server" required-with-options="Push">
            <role>Collects data for reporting</role>
        </supports-tx>
    </actor>

    <actor id="MeasureIntermediary" groups="MeasureSource MeasureConsumer">
        <name>Measure Intermediary</name>
        <description>The Measure Intermediary is a grouping of a Measure Source with a Measure Consumer.</description>
        <overview>This actor represents the composition of a <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> with a <ref actor='MeasureSource'/>.

The Measure Intermediary role can aggregate data from multiple Measure Sources.  Data from Measure Sources may
be pulled in by the Intermediary, pushed to the Intermediary by the Measure Source, or may be pushed from a
Measure Source via a dump.

Using the Dump option with a Measure Intermediary provides a Push or Pull mechanism to transfer
non-FHIR data or FHIR bulk data.  The Measure Intermediary can then convert the dump data into FHIR data that can be
served up to Measure Consumers in a format that is compliant with the requirements of a Measure Source.

The Measure Intermediary may also provide the capabilities of a Measure Consumer to enable data to be
reported at an aggregated level.

The Measure Intermediary role may aggregate data from other Measure Intermediaries.  Since the Intermediary
is exposing a Measure Source capability this method allows data to be aggregated in a hierarchy such as:

    - Supporting multiple data inputs within a single facility to create a complete measure from multiple partial reports,
    - Enabling aggregation of data for Groups of hospitals in a health system, a hospital service area, or referral region,
    - Aggregating to county or state levels for local and regional Public Health agencies
    - Communicating aggregated data to National / Federal Agencies such as CDC or FEMA.


#### Bridging between Incompatible Options
In networking parlance, a Bridge is a system that connects between different protocols.  The different options in this Implementation Guide
can create incompatibilities, but these can be bridged by an Intermediary.

For example, a Measure Intermediary that implements the Dump and Pull Options in the Measure Consumer, that groups with a Measure Source
implementing the Push and API Options can bridge bridge between a Measure Source implementing the Dump and Push options to enable
communication with a Measure Consumer implementing the API and Push options.

![Bridge](Bridge.svg)

#### Measure Repository
A Measure Respository is simply a FHIR Server.  A FHIR Server that supports CRUD operations on MeasureReport and Measure effectively implements both the Measure Consumer with the API and Push Options
and the Measure Source actor implementing the Pull and API Options.

![FHIR Server](FHIRServer.svg)


        </overview>
    </actor>
    <transaction id="PULL-TX" standards="FHIR-R4 RFC-7230 NDJSON">
        <name>Query Measure</name>
        <description>The Query Measure transaction allows a Measure Consumer to
periodically query about the availability of a resource from an Measure Source.</description>
        <!-- like steps, messages can nest to support activation lines -->
        <message from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureSource">
            <name>Search Request</name>
            <description></description>
            <trigger id="TRIGGER1">
                <name>Periodic Reporting Interval Elapsed, or a Query is Initiated by User/System</name>
            </trigger>
            <semantics>
                <description>If the API Option is supported, the Measure Consumer sends a query
using an HTTP GET or POST transaction to the Measure Source requesting information on
available resources.

If the Storage Option is supported, the Measure Consumer will read resources from external storage
using appropriate operations for the storage in use (e.g., SFTP/S3/Blob/File).</description>
                <overview></overview>
            </semantics>
            <action by="MeasureConsumer">
                <name>Measure Consumer requests data from a Measure Source.</name>
                <description>When the API Option is implemented, the Measure Consumer performs a FHIR Search operation
to retrieve the selected resources.  When the Storage Option is implemented, the Measure Consumer reads resources from external
storage specified by the Measure Source.
                </description>
                <overview></overview>
            </action>
            <result>
                <name>Search Response</name>
                <description>The Measure Source returns the results.</description>
                <trigger id="TRIGGER-1a">
                   <name>Resources have been requested by a Measure Consumer.</name>
                </trigger>
                <semantics>
                    <description>The Measure Source responds with requested resources.</description>
                    <overview>The resources will conform to the profiles for the
Bed Measure Report or Device Measure Report described eslewhere in this Implementation Guide</overview>
                </semantics>
                <action by="MeasureSource">
                    <name>Measure Source returns Resources</name>
                    <description>The Measure Source returns the requested resource.</description>
                    <overview>When the API Option is used, the Measure Source will return the selected resources and
an appropriate success response in a Bundle resource following the protocol for the Search operation.  When the Dump
option is used, the Measure Source will return all resources requested by the Measure Consumer.
                    </overview>
                </action>
            </result>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <transaction id="PUSH-TX" standards="FHIR-R4 RFC-7230 NDJSON">
        <name>Produce Measure</name>
        <description>The Produce Measure transaction allows an Measure Source to
periodically report on availability of resources to a Measure Consumer.</description>
        <message from="MeasureSource" to="MeasureConsumer">
            <name>Push Measure</name>
            <description></description>
            <trigger id="TRIGGER2">
                <name>Periodic Reporting Interval elapsed</name>
                <description>brief description (markdown)</description>
                <overview>more detailed description (markdown)</overview>
            </trigger>
            <action by="MeasureSource">
                <name>Measure Source reports a Resource</name>
                <description>The Measure Source creates resources and sends them to a Measure Consumer</description>
                <overview>When the API option is implemented, the Measure Source performs the FHIR create
operation on the MeasureReport resource at a Measure Consumer.  When the Dump option is implemented, the Measure Source
writes the MeasureReport data to external storage specified by the Measure Consumer.
</overview>
            </action>
            <action by="MeasureConsumer">
                <name>The Measure Consumer Accepts Resource</name>
                <description>When the API option is used, the Measure Consumer reports
success using 200 OK, 201 Created, or 204 No Content to indicate a successful update.  When the Dump option is
used, the Measure Consumer reports success using the native protocols for the external storage subsytem.
</description>
                <overview/>
            </action>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <transaction id="REPORT-TX" standards="RFC-7230">
        <name>Communicate Results</name>
        <description>The Communicate Results transaction allows users (e.g., Public Health Officials) to view current resource availability,
or other systems to access resource availability data.</description>
        <message from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureConsumer">
            <name>Communicate Measure</name>
            <description>Upon completion of this transaction, resource availability data will have been communicated to a
user or system. This can be demonstrated by generation of a report, summary, or other artifact, or by transmission of resource
availability data or some computation over it to another system.
            </description>
            <overview>This requirement can be met by a Measure Consumer that consumes and displays data in a Web Browser, consumes data
            and transmits it in another format to a public health agency (e.g., using the CDC CSV format), or as a Measure
            Intermediary that consumes data from one system and communicates it to another, or transforms it and communicates it back
            to the original system or to another system.
            </overview>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <content id="bed-location">
        <name>bed-location</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Location Resource describing a reported upon Bed in a Bed Measure Report</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="supporting-device">
        <name>Supporting Device</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Device Resource describing a reported upon Device in Device Measure Report</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="resource-location">
        <name>Resource Location</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Location Resource describing the physical location (e.g., building)
where a bed or device is located</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="audit-event-write">
        <name>Audit Event Write</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of an AuditEvent Resource reporting a write on a resource.</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="audit-event-read">
        <name>Audit Event Read</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of an AuditEvent Resource reporting a read on a resource.</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
</profile>
