<profile xmlns="http://ainq.com/ig-definition" id="SANER" chapter='1' codingsystems="SanerBedType" valuesets="BedLocationOperationalStatus BedProperty BedType">
	<domain id="AI">
	    <org>Audacious Inquiry</org>
	    <name>Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response</name>
	    <description></description>
	    <overview file="SANER-overview.md"/>
	</domain>
    <name>Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response</name>
    <description>The Situational Awareness for Novel Epidemic Response Implementation Guide enables transmission
of high level situational awareness information from inpatient facilities to centralized data repositories
to support the treatment of novel influenza-like illness.

![The SANER Project Logo](SANERLogo.png)

**Fighting COVID-19 with FHIR®**
    </description>
    <!-- overview is optional -->
    <overview file="SANER-overview.md"/>
    <!-- option is optional and repeatable -->
    <option id="Dump">
        <name>Storage Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the Storage Option supports the ability to exchange FHIR Resources through
various means of simple data transfer, rather than directly through a FHIR API call. This include mechanisms such
as SFTP, S3 Blob Storage, Azure Blob Storage, a Message Queue, https: File Download, File System dumps, or Direct Messages with a
data payload. Supported formats include JSON, XML and NDJSON.
        </description>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>A <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> actor implementing the Storage Option uses external storage to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>A <ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> actor implementing the Storage Option uses external storage to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="API">
        <name>API Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the API Option supports the
ability to exchange FHIR Resources using [FHIR RESTful APIs](http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/http.html).</description>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>An <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> actor implementing the API option uses FHIR RESTful APIs to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An <ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> actor implementing the API option uses FHIR RESTful APIs to communicate data.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Push">
	    <name>Push Option</name>
	    <description>An actor implementing the Push Option supports the periodic push of resources
describing the current status of health delivery resources to a centralized collection point.
	    </description>
	    <overview/>
	    <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
	        <description>A Measure Source implementing the Push Option periodically sends updates to a
<ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> using the <ref tx='PUSH-TX'/> transaction.</description>
	    </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Push Option periodically recieves updates from the
<ref actor='MeasureSource'/> using the <ref tx='PUSH-TX'/> transaction.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Pull">
        <name>Pull Option</name>
        <description>An actor implementing the Pull Option supports the periodic pull resources
describing the current status of selected health delivery resources.</description>
        <overview/>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
           <description>A Measure Source implementing the Pull Option is periodically queried by an
<ref actor='MeasureConsumer'/> using the <ref tx='PULL-TX'/> transaction to enable collection of the current status.
</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Pull Option periodically queries a
<ref actor='MeasureSource'/> using the <ref tx='PULL-TX'/> transaction to enable collection of the current status.
            </description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Bed">
        <name>Bed Option</name>
        <description>An actor supporting the Bed Option can describe the status of beds.</description>
        <overview/>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>An Measure Source implementing the Bed Option generates data on beds.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Bed Option consumes data about beds.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Asset">
        <name>Asset Option</name>
        <description>An actor supporting the Asset Option can describe the status of non-bed treatment
resources, such as ventilators, respirators, infusion pumps, monitoring equipment, et cetera</description>
        <overview/>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>An Measure Source implementing the Asset Option generates data on other Assets
(e.g., ventilators, respirators, PPE, and other equipment or supplies).</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Consumer implementing the Asset Option consumes data about other Assets
(e.g., ventilators, respirators, PPE, and other equipment or supplies).</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <option id="Group">
        <name>Group Option</name>
        <description>An actor supporting the Group Option can work with Group resources representing individual strata
values extracted from a Measure Report</description>
        <participant actor='MeasureSource'>
            <description>An Measure Source implementing the Group Option can produce reports using the Group Resource.</description>
        </participant>
        <participant actor='MeasureConsumer'>
            <description>An Measure Source implementing the Group Option can consume reports using the Group Resource.</description>
        </participant>
    </option>
    <!-- standard is repeatable -->
    <standard id="FHIR-R4">
        <name>HL7 FHIR Release 4.0</name>
        <url>http://www.hl7.org/FHIR/R4</url>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-7230">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc7230.html</url>
        <name>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP/1.1</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-7540">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc7540.html</url>
        <name>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP/2</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-3986">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.html</url>
        <name>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-4627">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc4627.html</url>
        <name>The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="RFC-6585">
        <url>https://ietf.org/rfc/rfc6585.html</url>
        <name>Additional HTTP Status Codes</name>
    </standard>
    <standard id="NDJSON">
        <url>http://ndjson.org/</url>
        <name>Newline Delimited JSON</name>
    </standard>

    <!-- usecase is optional and repeatable -->
    <usecase id="GETBEDS" actors="MeasureSource MeasureConsumer" transactions="PULL-TX PUSH-TX" content="bed-measure-report bed-device-report bed-group supporting-device bed-location">
	    <name>Collecting Bed Measures</name>
        <description>This use case addresses the exchange of data from Facilities to a Centralized
reporting system for Public Health</description>
	    <!-- overview is optional -->
	    <overview>Overview TBD</overview>
	    <step id="BED-STEP1" from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureSource" returns="now">
            <name>Measure Repository Initiates Search</name>
            <description>The Measure Repository identifies features associated with a group of
bed or device resources that it wishes to collect data about.  For example, the Measure Repository can
request information about ICU, med/surg, or ED beds available or in use.</description>
            <overview>TBD</overview>
	        <return id="BED-STEP2" from="MeasureSource" to="MeasureConsumer" returns="now">
	            <name>Measure Source Reports Aggregate Data</name>
	            <description>The Measure Source reports aggregate data about a group of beds or devices based
	                on specified bed or device characteristics</description>
	            <overview>TBD</overview>
	        </return>
	    </step>
    </usecase>
    <usecase id="VIEWREPORTS" actors="MeasureConsumer" transactions="REPORT-TX" content="bed-measure-report device-measure-report bed-group supporting-device bed-location">
        <name>Reporting on A Measure</name>
        <description>TBD</description>
        <!-- overview is optional -->
        <overview>TBD</overview>
        <step id="Reporting-STEP1" from="Public Health User" to="MeasureConsumer" returns="now">
            <name>User Initiates Search</name>
            <description>The Public Health User navigates to a web page where collected data is reported.</description>
            <overview>TBD</overview>
            <step id="Aggregating-STEP2" from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureSource" returns="now">
                <name>Measure Consumer gathers data from one or Measure Sources</name>
                <description>The Measure Consumer gathers and aggregates data from one or more Measure Sources.</description>
                <overview>The specific ordering in which gathering and aggregation is performed is not further specified
by this implementation guide. It is shown as occuring after the user initiates the query here, but could have occured
prior.</overview>
            </step>
            <return>
                <name>Display Results</name>
                <description>The Measure Consumer displays an overview of aggregated regional results to the
user, and additional links which enable navigation to finer grained or alternative displays.</description>
                <overview>Data can be displayed as aggregated or fine-grained status information based
on the current focus of the public health user.  It may be shown as a map, a table, or a graph.</overview>
            </return>
        </step>
        <step id="Reporting-STEP2" from="Public Health User" to="MeasureConsumer" returns="now">
            <name>User refines Focus or Form of Display</name>
            <description>The Public Health User selects a new form of display (e.g., Map, table or graph) or refines their
focus (e.g., wider or smaller region).</description>
            <overview>TBD</overview>
            <return>
                <name>Display Refined Results</name>
                <description>The Measure Repository modifies the users focus and reporting format</description>
                <overview>TBD</overview>
            </return>
        </step>
    </usecase>
    <!--  Other Use Cases can describe options -->
    <actor id="MeasureSource">
        <name>Measure Source</name>
        <description>The Measure Source Actor reports results for a single facility, collection of facilities
        or aggragated data for a region</description>
        <!-- overview is optional -->
        <overview>TBD</overview>
        <supports-tx transaction="PULL-TX" as="server" required-with-options="Pull">
            <role>Reports on selected data in response to a query.</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PUSH-TX" as="client" required-with-options="Push">
            <role>Periodically generates data for a Measure Consumer.</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="COLLECT-R1" at-least-one="Pull Push"/>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="COLLECT-R2" at-least-one="API Dump"/>
    </actor>

    <actor id="MeasureConsumer">
        <name>Measure Consumer</name>
        <description>The Measure Consumer provides access to aggregated or fine-grained
data gathered from one or more Measure Sources.
        </description>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="REPORT-R1" at-least-one="Pull Push"/>
        <!-- requirement is optional and can repeat -->
        <requires id="REPORT-R1" at-least-one="API Dump"/>

        <requires-tx transaction="REPORT-TX" as="self">
            <role>Display or transmits reports using availability data</role>
        </requires-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PULL-TX" as="client" required-with-options="Pull">
            <role>Collects data for reporting</role>
        </supports-tx>
        <supports-tx transaction="PUSH-TX" as="server" required-with-options="Push">
            <role>Collects data for reporting</role>
        </supports-tx>
    </actor>

    <actor id="MeasureIntermediary" groups="MeasureSource MeasureConsumer">
        <name>Measure Intermediary</name>
        <description>The Measure Intermediary is a grouping of a Measure Source with a Measure Consumer.</description>
        <overview>This actor represents the composition of a <ref actor='MeasureSource'/> with a <ref actor='MeasureSource'/>.

#### Bridging between Incompatible Options
A Measure Consumer that implements the Dump and Pull Options that is grouped with a Measure Source implementing the Push and API
Options can be used as a bridge to adapt a Meaure Source implementing the Dump and Push options to communicate with a Measure
Consumer implementing the API and Push options.

![Bridge](Bridge.svg)

#### Measure Repository
A Measure Consumer that implements the API Option and Push Option that is grouped with a Measure Source implementing the Pull and API
Options is essentially the definition of a FHIR Server.

![FHIR Server](FHIRServer.svg)

#### Measure to Group Slicer
A Measure Consumer that implements the API and Pull Option can be grouped with a Measure Source implementing the Push, API and
Fine-Grained option to "slice and dice" Measure Reports into Groups, populating a Measure Consumer with fine-grained data from
a Measure Source.  This adapter can be used to add the Fine Grained Option to a Measure Repository.

![Slicer](Slicer.svg)

        </overview>
    </actor>
    <transaction id="PULL-TX" standards="FHIR-R4 RFC-7230 NDJSON">
        <name>Query Measure</name>
        <description>The Query Measure transaction allows a Measure Consumer to
periodically query about the availability of a resource from an Measure Source.</description>
        <!-- like steps, messages can nest to support activation lines -->
        <message from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureSource">
            <name>Search Request</name>
            <description></description>
            <trigger id="TRIGGER1">
                <name>Periodic Reporting Interval Elapsed, or a Query is Initiated by User/System</name>
            </trigger>
            <semantics>
                <description>If the API Option is supported, the Measure Consumer sends a query
using an HTTP GET or POST transaction to the Measure Source requesting information on
available resources.

If the Storage Option is supported, the Measure Consumer will read resources from external storage
using appropriate operations for the storage in use (e.g., SFTP/S3/Blob/File).</description>
                <overview></overview>
            </semantics>
            <action by="MeasureConsumer">
                <name>Measure Consumer requests data from a Measure Source.</name>
                <description>When the API Option is implemented, the Measure Consumer performs a FHIR Search operation
to retrieve the selected resources.  When the Storage Option is implemented, the Measure Consumer reads resources from external
storage specified by the Measure Source.
                </description>
                <overview></overview>
            </action>
            <result>
                <name>Search Response</name>
                <description>The Measure Source returns the results.</description>
                <trigger id="TRIGGER-1a">
                   <name>Resources have been requested by a Measure Consumer.</name>
                </trigger>
                <semantics>
                    <description>The Measure Source responds with requested resources.</description>
                    <overview>The resources will conform to the profiles for the
Bed Measure Report or Device Measure Report described eslewhere in this Implementation Guide</overview>
                </semantics>
                <action by="MeasureSource">
                    <name>Measure Source returns Resources</name>
                    <description>The Measure Source returns the requested resource.</description>
                    <overview>When the API Option is used, the Measure Source will return the selected resources and
an appropriate success response in a Bundle resource following the protocol for the Search operation.  When the Dump
option is used, the Measure Source will return all resources requested by the Measure Consumer.
                    </overview>
                </action>
            </result>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <transaction id="PUSH-TX" standards="FHIR-R4 RFC-7230 NDJSON">
        <name>Produce Measure</name>
        <description>The Produce Measure transaction allows an Measure Source to
periodically report on availability of resources to a Measure Consumer.</description>
        <message from="MeasureSource" to="MeasureConsumer">
            <name>Push Measure</name>
            <description></description>
            <trigger id="TRIGGER2">
                <name>Periodic Reporting Interval elapsed</name>
                <description>brief description (markdown)</description>
                <overview>more detailed description (markdown)</overview>
            </trigger>
            <action by="MeasureSource">
                <name>Measure Source reports a Resource</name>
                <description>The Measure Source creates resources and sends them to a Measure Consumer</description>
                <overview>When the API option is implemented, the Measure Source performs the FHIR create
operation on the MeasureReport resource at a Measure Consumer.  When the Dump option is implemented, the Measure Source
writes the MeasureReport data to external storage specified by the Measure Consumer.

When the Group option is implemented, the Measure Source also generates Group resources.  The Measure Source may
be configured to disable generation of MeasureReport resources (e.g., when used to add Group capabilities to an
existing server), but must be able to demostrate creation of the MeasureReport resources matching the Group.
</overview>
            </action>
            <action by="MeasureConsumer">
                <name>The Measure Consumer Accepts Resource</name>
                <description>When the API option is used, the Measure Consumer reports
success using 200 OK, 201 Created, or 204 No Content to indicate a successful update.  When the Dump option is
used, the Measure Consumer reports success using the native protocols for the external storage subsytem.
</description>
                <overview>When the Group option is implemented, the Measure Consumer also accepts Group resources.</overview>
            </action>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <transaction id="REPORT-TX" standards="RFC-7230">
        <name>Communicate Results</name>
        <description>The Communicate Results transaction allows users (e.g., Public Health Officials) to view current resource availability,
or other systems to access resource availability data.</description>
        <message from="MeasureConsumer" to="MeasureConsumer">
            <name>Communicate Measure</name>
            <description>Upon completion of this transaction, resource availability data will have been communicated to a
user or system. This can be demonstrated by generation of a report, summary, or other artifact, or by transmission of resource
availability data or some computation over it to another system.
            </description>
            <overview>This requirement can be met by a Measure Consumer that consumes and displays data in a Web Browser, consumes data
            and transmits it in another format to a public health agency (e.g., using the CDC CSV format), or as a Measure
            Intermediary that consumes data from one system and communicates it to another, or transforms it and communicates it back
            to the original system or to another system.
            </overview>
        </message>
    </transaction>

    <content id="bed-measure-report">
        <name>Bed Measure Report</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a MeasureReport resource describing Bed Measures</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="device-measure-report">
        <name>Device Measure Report</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a MeasureReport resource describing Device Measures</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="bed-group">
        <name>Bed Group</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Group resource reporting Bed Counts</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="device-group">
        <name>Device Group</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Group resource reporting Device Counts</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>

    <content id="bed-location">
        <name>bed-location</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Location Resource describing a reported upon Bed in a Bed Measure Report</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="supporting-device">
        <name>Supporting Device</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Device Resource describing a reported upon Device in Device Measure Report</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="resource-location">
        <name>Resource Location</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of a Location Resource describing the physical location (e.g., building)
where a bed or device is located</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="audit-event-write">
        <name>Audit Event Write</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of an AuditEvent Resource reporting a write on a resource.</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
    <content id="audit-event-read">
        <name>Audit Event Read</name>
        <description>This content profile describes the structure of an AuditEvent Resource reporting a read on a resource.</description>
        <overview></overview>
    </content>
</profile>
